What if just one
lifestyle change
could help you
avoid getting cancer,
or diabetes,
or heart disease,
or high blood pressure?
This one change could cut
your risk of chronic disease
and add years to your life.
Well, the simple solution to
so many of these problems
is to eat a healthy diet.
In other words, one centered
around whole plant foods.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I'm your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
There is a lot of demand for
information about fasting.
And as luck would have it,
more and more research
is released every day.
Today we look at the practice of
fasting to reverse type 2 diabetes.
Currently, nearly half a billion
adults have diabetes,
and a 50% increase is
expected in another generation.
I've got tons of videos on
the best diets for diabetes,
but what about no diet at all?
More than a century ago,
fasting was said to bring
about the cure of diabetes,
speedily arresting its development
and causing complete disappearance
of all its manifestations
in several days or weeks.
Even so, starvation is
guaranteed to lead to
the complete disappearance
of you, if kept up long enough.
What's the point of fasting it away,
if it's just going to come raging back
as soon as you restart the diet
that caused it in the first place?
Might it be useful to kind of
kickstart a healthier diet?
Let's see what the science says.
Type 2 diabetes has long been
recognized as a disease of excess,
a disease of the idle rich,
by which they mean anyone
who doesn't practice
sustained vigorous
bodily exertion every day,
and earning enough to regularly
eat more than they need.
So diabetes is preventable,
but then maybe it's also treatable.
If we are dying of overeating, maybe
we can be saved by undereating.
Remarkably this was suggested about
2,000 years ago in an Ayurvedic text.
Diabetics were encouraged
to live like a saint, walk for, oh,
800 or 900 miles, dig a pond, or live
only on cow dung and cow urine.
That reminds me of the Rollo diet
for diabetes proposed in 1797,
composed of a diet of rancid meat.
That was on top of the ipecac-like drugs
he used to produce
severe sickness and vomiting.
Anything that produces sickness has
a temporary effect in relieving diabetes
by diminishing the
quantity of food eaten.
And his diet plan —
congealed blood for lunch
and spoiled meat for dinner —
certainly had that effect.
Similar benefits were seen in
diabetics during the siege of Paris
in the Franco-Prussian War,
leading to the advice to
'mangez le moins possible'
(eat as little as possible).
That was formalized into
the Allen Starvation treatment,
considered to be the greatest medical
advance in the treatment of diabetes
prior to the discovery of insulin.
Before insulin, there was the Allen Era.
He noted reports in the clinical literature
of even severe diabetics clearing up
on wasting diseases like tuberculosis,
so he decided to put it to the test.
He found that even the
most severe type of diabetes,
he could clear sugar from
people's urine within 10 days.
Of course, that's the easy part.
It's maintaining it
once you start eating again,
for which he stuck to two principles:
keeping them underweight
and restricting the quantity of fat.
A severe diabetic can be
symptom-free for days or weeks,
but add some butter or olive oil and
the disease can come raging back.
As I covered before, diabetes
is a disease of fat toxicity.
Infuse fat into people's
veins through an IV,
and by using a high-tech
type of MRI scanner,
you can show in real time the buildup
of fat in muscle cells within hours,
accompanied by an increase
in insulin resistance.
The same thing happens when you put
people on a high-fat diet for three days,
or even just one day,
or even just a single meal can increase
insulin resistance within six hours.
Acute dietary fat intake rapidly
increases insulin resistance.
Why do we care?
Because insulin resistance
in our muscles, in the context
of too many calories, leads to
the buildup of liver fat, which leads
to the buildup of fat in the pancreas,
which is eventually what
causes diabetes.
Type 2 diabetes can now
be understood as a state
of excess fat in the
liver and pancreas
and remains reversible for at least
10 years in most individuals.
Put people on a very low-calorie
diet, 700 calories a day,
and fat can get sucked
out of your muscle cells,
and you get a corresponding
boost in insulin sensitivity.
Fat is then sucked out of your liver,
and if you keep it up the fat gets
sucked out of your pancreas.
And if you catch it early enough
that can mean a reversal
of your type 2 diabetes, meaning
normal sugars on a normal diet.
With the loss of 15% of body weight,
nearly 90% of those who've had
type 2 diabetes for less than four
years can achieve remission,
where it may only be reversible in 50%
of those who've lived with the disease
for longer than eight years.
That's better than bariatric surgery,
where those losing even more weight
only got 62 and 26% remissions.
Your forks are better
than the surgeon's knives.
Here's how much weight you have to
lose to achieve various remission rates
for those who've had diabetes
for an average of three years.
Lose about 30 pounds and most
newly diagnosed type 2 diabetics
can reverse their disease. So an
extended bout of physician-supervised,
water-only fasting could get you there,
but you have to maintain
the weight loss.
One of the things we
can say with certainty
is that if you regain the weight,
you regain your diabetes.
To bring it full circle,
the initial euphoria about
medicine's greatest miracle,
the discovery of insulin in 1921,
soon gave way to the realization
that while it was literally a life-saver
for type 1 diabetics, the use of insulin
on its own in type 2 diabetics
would not be enough to prevent
the later onset of complications
like kidney failure, blindness,
stroke, amputations.
So, as argued by one the most famous
diabetes pioneers, Elliot Joslin,
self-discipline on diet and exercise,
as it was in the days prior to insulin,
should be central to the
management of diabetes.
Did you know that
caloric restriction
can boost levels of brain-
derived neurotrophic factor,
otherwise known as BDNF?
In fact, I just wrote
a chapter on it
in my upcoming book,
"How Not to Age".
Anyway, here's the story.
For over a century, fasting has
been espoused as a treatment
of supposed “great utility in
the preservation of health,”
especially rejuvenating the body,
but above all the mind.
But fast people even just 18 hours,
and they get all hungry and irritable.
After one or two days positive mood
goes down, negative mood goes up,
and by 72 hours people
can feel sad, self-blaming,
and suffer a loss in libido.
But then something
strange starts to happen.
After a few days, people experience
a “fasting-induced mood enhancement…
decreased anxiety, depression,
fatigue, and improved vigor.”
And that’s what studies tend
to show across the board.
Once you get over the hump,
fasters frequently experience
“an increased level of vigilance and…
mood improvement,
a subjective feeling of well-being,
and sometimes [even] euphoria.”
And no wonder, as by
then your endorphin levels
may shoot up nearly 50 percent.
This enhancement of mood,
alertness, and calm
makes a certain amount
of evolutionary sense.
Yeah, your body wants you
to feel crappy initially
so you continue eating day
to day when food is available,
but if you go a couple days
without food your body realizes
it can’t have you moping back
in the cave—you’ve got to
get motivated to get out
there and find some calories.
So, can fasting be used for
mood disorders like depression?
Yeah, it’s great that you
can get people to feel better
after a few days of fasting,
but the critical question
revolves around “the persistence
of mood improvement over time”
once you start eating again.
You don’t know until...
you put it to the test.
Interestingly, the little published
evidence we have comes out of
Japan and the former Soviet Union,
and some of it is just ridiculous.
Ten days of fasting, but they
also kept them in bed all day
completely isolated, with no
contact with the outside world.
So, if people got better or
worse it would be impossible
to tease out the effects of
just the fasting component.
But they did apparently get
better with efficacy supposedly
demonstrated in 31 out of 36
patients suffering from depression.
They conclude that fasting
therapy may provide an alternative
to the use of antidepressant drugs,
considering it “a kind of shock therapy.”
People are so relieved
to just be eating again,
to get out of solitary confinement,
to even just get out of bed
they report feeling better.
Yeah, but that was at
the time of discharge.
How did they feel the next day,
the next week, the next month?
Fasting is by definition unsustainable,
so ideally what we want to see
are some kind of longer-lasting effects.
So, what the researchers did was
follow-up with a few hundred patients,
not just a few months later
but a few years later.
Of the 69 who were evidently
suffering from depression,
90 percent reported feeling
good or excellent results
at the end of the 10-day
fast and remarkably, years later
87 percent of the 62 that replied
claimed that they were
still doing good.
Now there was no control
group, so we don’t know
if they would have done just
as well or better without the fast,
and it was just self-reports,
so maybe there was response bias
where you try to please the researchers,
or maybe they were afraid
otherwise they’d get
sent back to the hole.
We have no idea, but we
do have good evidence
for the short-term mood benefits.
The question is why.
In addition to the endorphins when
you fast and the surge in serotonin,
the so-called happiness hormone,
there is a bump in BDNF,
brain-derived neurotrophic factor,
considered to play a crucial
role in mood disorders.
And it’s not just because
you perk up rodents with it.
Humans with major
depression have lower levels
circulating in their blood stream.
Autopsy studies of suicide victims
show only about half the BDNF
in certain key brain
regions compared to controls,
suggesting it may play an
important role in suicidal behavior.
You can boost BDNF with
antidepressant drugs
and electroshock, or with calorie
restriction—a 70 percent boost
in levels after three months cutting 25
percent of calories out of their daily diet.
What effect does fasting
and a plant-based diet
have on traumatic brain
injury and migraines?
Let’s find out.
An uncontrolled and unpublished study
purported to show a beneficial effect
of fasting on migraine headaches,
but fasting may be more likely
to trigger a migraine than help it.
In fact, skipped meals
are among one of the most
consistently identified
dietary triggers
of headaches in general.
In a review of hundreds of fasts at the
TrueNorth Health Center in California,
the incidence of headache was nearly
one in three, but TrueNorth also
published a remarkable case
report on post-traumatic headache.
The CDC estimates that more
than a million Americans sustain
traumatic brain injuries every
year, and chronic pain
is a common complication,
as in like three-quarters
suffering such an injury.
There are drugs, of course, to treat it.
There are always drugs.
And if that doesn't work, surgery:
cutting the nerves to your head
to stop the pain. Well, what
about fasting and plants?
A highly debilitating condition,
difficult to manage,
a 52-year-old woman
presents with unremitting,
chronic post-traumatic headache.
And when I say chronic, I mean
chronic---pain for 16 years---
but who then achieved
long-term relief following fasting,
followed by an exclusively plant-based
diet, free of added sugar, oil, or salt.
Before then she had tried drug
after drug, after drug, after drug,
after drug with no relief, suffering
in constant pain her entire life.
Started out in constant pain,
but then after the fast,
the intensity of her pain was cut in
half, and though she was still having
daily headaches, at least there
were some pain-free periods.
Six months later she tried it again,
and eventually her headaches
were mild, under 10 minutes,
and infrequent,
and she continued that way
months and even years later.
Now, of course, it's hard
to disentangle the effects
of the fasting from the effects of
the whole food plant-based diet
she remained on
those ensuing years.
You've heard of analgesics---painkillers.
Well, there are some foods that may be
pro-algesic: pain promoting, such
as foods high in arachidonic acid,
which includes include
meats, dairy, and eggs.
So the lowering of arachidonic acid,
from which our body makes a range
of pro-inflammatory compounds,
may be accomplished by eating
a more plant-based diet.
So maybe that contributed
to the benefit in
the fasting case.
Whereas many plant foods are high
in anti-inflammatory components.
So in terms of migraine headaches,
more plant foods and less animal foods
may help, but you don't know
until you put it to the test.
The researchers figured a plant-based
diet may offer the best of both worlds,
so they designed a randomized,
controlled crossover study
where those with recurrent
migraines were randomized
to eat a strictly plant-based
diet or to take a placebo pill.
And then the groups switched.
During the placebo phase
half said the pain got better,
half said the pain remained the same
or got worse, but during the dietary
portion they almost all got better.
During that first block, the diet group
experienced significant improvements
in headache number, pain intensity,
days with headaches, and a
reduction in the amount
of painkillers they needed to take.
In fact, it worked a little too good.
Many individuals were
unwilling to complete the study
by returning to their previous diets.
Remember, they were supposed to
go back to their regular diets
and take a pill instead,
but they felt so much better that
they were like, "No way, José."
And we've seen this with other trials,
where those trying plant-based diets
felt so good, they often refused to
abandon them, screwing up the study.
So plant-based diets can
sometimes work a little too well.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts Podcast
landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
My latest two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”,
available on e-book, audiobook,
or actual book.
And the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”,
with more than 100 recipes for
delicious and nutritious meals.
All the proceeds I receive from
the sales of my books go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.